A child's leg was cut off 31,000 years ago, they lived for years.
Put your hand on your shin, feel the long bone just under the skin and the thinner one beside it.
Now imagine the lower half of that leg simply gone, not lost in a hospital with a
mask over your face and a machine counting your heartbeat, but in the wet heat of a rainforest
31,000 years ago with a sharpened stone and the people who love you leaning in clothes.
Your first instinct is probably the blood, the pain, the moment the blade
goes through and that moment would have been terrible but it is not the part that should have killed
this child.
The thing that should have killed them comes later in the weeks a wound stays open
in a place crawling with infection and in the years afterward when a person who can no
longer walk has to survive in a world that never stops moving.
The bones of this child still exist and the bones say they lived for a long
time.
By the end of this you'll know what most likely carried them through.
You'll also meet the scientists who think the whole story is being read wrong.
The child lies buried in a cave called Liang Tebo in the forested limestone hills of
eastern Borneo in what is now Indonesia.
A team led by archaeologists Tim Maloney and Maxim Aubert reached the grave in early 2020 just
before the world closed its borders.
When they came back the following year, one of them a bone specialist named Melendri looked closely
at where the left leg ended and noticed something that didn't fit.
The leg hadn't been crushed.
When a boulder falls on a limb or an animal takes it the bone shatters its splinters in a
dozen directions.
This wasn't that.
The two bones of the lower leg the thick tibia and the slimmer fibula beside it ended at
the same clean line cut straight across the way a bone looks when something sharp goes
through it on purpose.
Whoever ended that leg knew where to cut.
They went through skin muscle blood vessels and nerve without the child bleeding out
in front of them.
That alone tells you these were not simple people fumbling in the dark.
Someone in that group understood the inside of a body.
Then comes the wound.
You live in an age of clean bandages so it's easy to forget that for most of human
history the open wound not the injury was the executioner.
A cut limb in a forest is an open door and infection walks straight
through it fast often within days.
Look at the child's bone and there's no sign of it no spreading damage no scarring
of infection the wound closed someone kept it clean long enough to heal.
Nobody can hand you the exact recipe but Borneo is one of the richest plant worlds on the planet and
the people who live there knew it intimately.
India Dilkshall who studies ancient plant use points out that the forest holds its own medicine cabinet that
the fruit of a tree called pangium edgel poisonous if you eat it raw becomes useful as an antiseptic once it's
properly prepared whether that exact plant touched this exact wound no one can say.
What the bone says plainly is that someone somehow did the slow work of keeping a
wound clean in a place that punishes open skin.
So you now know two things the cut was made with knowledge the wound was tended
with care and you still don't know the hardest part.
This child did not heal in a week and walk away the lower leg bone that remained had grown
thin and smooth and reshaped itself the slow signature of bone that has been alive and used
in a changed body for years.
The researchers read those years in the bone somewhere between six and nine of them the child
was perhaps 12 when the leg was lost they lived to around 20.
Sit with what those years required in a world of hunter-gatherers survival is movement you follow
the food you climb the wet rock you cross the river when the season turns a person who cannot walk
cannot do any of it which means that for six to nine years somebody else did it for them somebody carried
or waited or went out and came back with food for a person who could not go and get it themselves not
once in a moment of pity day after day season after season for most
of a childhood that is the thing the bone is really telling you not
that a blade was sharp that a group of people decided again and again to
keep someone who could give them nothing back here is where it would be easy to
round it all up into a perfect story so here is the honest part not
every scientist agrees this was surgery in 2023 a group of orthopedic
surgeons people who take limbs off for a living wrote a formal reply arguing that an ordinary
accident could explain these bones just as well maybe a bad break that the body or the
forest finished on its own they felt the original team had too quickly for the
dramatic answer the team wrote back they explained they had started exactly
where the critics wanted with the boring explanations the simple fracture the natural causes
and ruled them out one by one because a clean cut through both bones at the same line
doesn't behave like an accident they put the three-dimensional scans of the leg online so
anyone in the world can look for themselves you don't have to settle that argument to
feel the floor underneath it strip the word surgery away entirely suppose for a
moment the critics are right and no one ever held a blade the bone still shows a child who lost a
leg and then lived growing for years afterward in a body that could not keep up however that leg was lost
the years that followed are not in dispute and those years still had to be paid for by other people
which means the oldest thing in this grave was never really the operation the
discovery isn't a technique it's a decision the decision to carry the one who
can't walk sitting in human hands tens of thousands of years before farming
before medicine before any of the markers usually called the beginning of civilization
it was already there in a cave in the rain so put your
hand back on your shin that leg the one you've been imagining gone was never
the hardest thing this child had to survive the blade was one terrible day
the years were the trial the long unglamorous stretch of being unable to
keep up and being kept anyway you come from people who did that who
looked at someone who slowed them down who cost them food and effort and time and chose
them anyway for years in the dark by the fire that choice is older
than almost everything you think of as human and some version of it is still in you
somewhere far from that cave on another continent and thousands of years apart
another body was healing wounds it had no business surviving kept alive
by the same stubborn ordinary care but that one is a story for next
time