you wake up when your body is ready.
No alarm, no notification, no meeting in 20 minutes.
The sun has barely touched the horizon and your body simply knows it is always
known.
For roughly 300,000 years, this was every single morning for your ancestors.
No schedule waiting, no boss, no inbox, just the world your people
and the slow unfolding of a day that looked almost nothing like yours.
So what did they actually do with all that time?
The answer will probably make you uncomfortable.
Anthropologist Marshall Salons famously called Hunter Gatherers the original affluent society, not
because they had much, but because they wanted little and the gap between what they needed and what the world provided was
surprisingly small.
His 1966 analysis of the Kung San people of the Kalahari Desert found that adults spent
an average of just 15 to 20 hours per week on subsistence activities, hunting, gathering,
preparing food, everything needed to survive.
15 to 20 hours per week.
You probably spend more than that commuting.
The rest of the time was not idle, but it was not what you would call productive either.
It was something older than productivity, something your nervous system still craves
and almost never gets.
Let's reconstruct a morning.
You rise with four or five others in your band.
Maybe a dozen people total are camp nearby.
The fire from the night before still breathes with a few orange coals.
Someone feeds it.
Someone else begins checking the small clay pots near the edge of the embers.
There is no rush.
There is no particular order to any of this.
Children are awake, but no one is managing them.